KAARTHIC PULOGARAJAH

2B MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Summary

- Proficiency in SolidWorks, PLC
 Programming, and Creo Parametric
 gained in a workplace environment
- Expertise in MATLAB, SolidWorks surface modelling, Arduino, C/C++, and HTML/CSS acquired through extensive personal projects
- Exceptional teamwork and communication skills obtained through design competitions and tutoring
- Strong analytic and problem solving skills developed while pursuing complex and challenging projects

Contact

■ kaarthicp@hotmail.com

kaarthicp.me

4 647-870-5145

in linkedin.com/in/kaarthicp

Awards

University of Toronto · 3rd place University of Toronto High School Design Competition

Created Rube Goldberg machine to extinguish a flame using only junk materials

International Taekwondo Federation · Black belt in Taekwondo

DECA Ontario · DECA Provincial Medallist

University of Waterloo · Math Contests - Distinction

Education

University of Waterloo

BASc Mechanical Engineering 2021 Relevant Courses: ME 212 Kinematics

Activities

The Reckoner of MGCI · Editorial Writer

Authored critical editorial articles relevant to school population

Youth Against Drugs · Anti-Substance Abuse Advocate

Raised awareness for substance abuse through school wide events

Employment

Alcohol Countermeasure Systems Inc.

Toronto, ON Jan 2018 to Apr 2018

Mechatronics Engineer

 Developed PLC software using Structured Text and Ladder Diagrams to control electromechanical devices-mass flow controllers, peristaltic pumps, solenoid valves

- Programmed PLC to control breathalyzer calibration machine capable of simulating human breathing
- Designed column protection device to protect production floor using SolidWorks
- Created and updated engineering drawings of new and existing parts for manufacturing

ESI Robotics and Automation

Toronto, ON May 2017 to Aug 2017

Robotics Designer

- Performed FEA of robot components and created a report outlining observations and recommendations
- Designed and 3D printed tensioning device to tighten timing belt mechanism using Creo Parametric
- Devised system to secure batteries to robot in a modular approach
- Assembled robots quickly and efficiently to meet deadline of delivering robots for tradeshow

Educare Tutoring

Toronto, ON Oct 2015 to Jun 2016

Math and Science Tutor

- Reinforced and improved middle school and high school students' understanding of core concepts in various subjects
- Developed strategies and schedules with each student to focus on long-term and short-term goals
- Gained professional communication experience by discussing strategies and plans with parents

Projects

Airplane Takeoff Trajectory

Mar 2018 to Apr 2018

- Conducted investigation into commercial aircraft and takeoff protocols to produce trajectory
 of takeoff
- Used techniques of calculus, linear algebra, and physics to create mathematical model of flight path
- Wrote MATLAB script to generate takeoff trajectory and calculate distance to aircraft

1315-MH Wind Tunnel

Sep 2015 to Jan 2016

- Designed frame of wind tunnel to hold force and wind speed sensors
- Co-authored a comprehensive proposal describing functionality, costs, and design of how to build wind tunnel
- Integrated differential pressure sensor with Arduino to measure wind speed inside tunnel
- Produced a mathematical model to relate sensor readings to true wind speed using experimental data

Planets Orbiting Simulation

Jul 2017 to Aug 2017

- Utilized **MATLAB** to create accurate simulation of nine planets orbiting the sun and calculate distance between planets
- Applied knowledge of parametric equations and rotation matrices to draw and rotate elliptical orbits

Formula Motorsports

Sep 2016 to Apr 2017

- Designed chain guard on **SolidWorks** to be machined and used to protect chain on 2017 FSAE competition car
- Machined FSAE car components using lathe and ensured parts were within design specification

SolidWorks Surface Modelling

Jan 2018 to Feb 2018

Used **SolidWorks** surface modelling features to model set of animal shaped tea infusers